Let me guess.
You must be Xerxes.
Come, Leonidas.
Let us reason together.
It would be a regrettable waste.
It would be nothing
short of madness,
were you, brave king, and your
valiant troops to perish.
All because of a simple
misunderstanding.
There is much our cultures
could share.
Haven't you noticed we've been sharing
our culture with you all morning?
Yours is a fascinating tribe.
Even now you are defiant,
in the face of annihilation.
In the presence of the god, it isn't
wise to stand against me, Leonidas.
Imagine what horrible fate
awaits my enemies
when I will gladly kill
any one of my own men for victory.
And I would die
for any one of mine.
You Greeks take pride
in your logic.
I suggest you employ it.
Consider the beautiful lands
you so vigorously defend.
Picture it reduced to ash
at my will.
Consider the fate of your women.
Clearly, you don't know our women.
I might as well have marched
them up here,
judging by what I've seen.
You have many slaves,
Xerxes,
but few warriors.
It won't be long
before they fear my spears...
...more than your whips.
It's not the lash they fear.
It is my divine power.
But I'm a generous god.
I can make you rich beyond
all measure.
I will make you warlord
of all Greece.
You'll carry my battle standard
to the heart of Europa.
Your Athenian rivals
will kneel at your feet.
If you will but kneel at mine.
You are generous...
...as you are divine.
King of kings. Such an offer
only a madman would refuse.
But the...
...the idea of kneeling it's...
you see...
Slaughtering of all those men of yours
has left a nasty cramp in my legs.
So kneeling will be hard
for me.
There will be no glory
in your sacrifice.
I will erase even the memory
of Sparta from the histories.
Every piece of Greek parchment
shall be burned.
Every Greek historian
and every scribe
shall have their eyes spun out
and their tongues cut from their mouths
whilst honoring the very name of Sparta
or Leonidas will be punishable by death.
The world will never know
you existed at all.
The world will know that free men
stood against a tyrrant.
That few stood against many.
And before this battle was over,
that even a God King can bleed.
You fought well today.
For a woman.
As did you.
Maybe you've been injured,
you weren't able to keep up with me.
Perhaps I was so far ahead,
you couldn't see me.
Or were you offering
your backside to the Thespians.
Jealousy...
...is not becoming my friend.
Move it, men!
Pile those Persians high.
For unless I miss my guess...
...we're in for one wild night.
They have served the dark will
of Persian kings for 500 years.
Eyes as dark as night.
Teeth filed to fangs.
Soulless.
The personal guard
to king Xerses himself.
The Persian warrior elite.
The deadliest fighting
force in all of Asia.
The Immortals.
The God King has betrayed
a fatal flaw.
Hybris.
Easy to taunt.
Easy to trick.
Before wounds and weariness
have taken their toll,
the mad king throws
the best he has at us.
Xerxes has taken the bait.
Spartans, push!
Immortals.
They put their name
to the test.
Father!
My king!
Arcadians, now!
Go!
Let's show the Spartans
what we can do.
Go!
They shout and curse,
stabbing wildly,
more brawlers
than warriors.
They make a wondrous
mess of things.
Brave amateurs.
They do their part.
Immortals.
They failed our kings' test.
And a man who fancies
himself a god...
...feels a very human chill
crawl up his spine.
For our king!
And our honored dead!
Whom will Xerxes dare
to send next?
There's nothing
that can stop us now.
Even the king allows himself
to hope for more than glory.
Such mad hope.
But there it is.
Against Asian endless hordes,
against all odds,
we can do it,
we can hold the Hot Gates.
We can win.
Dawn.
Whips crack.
Barbarians howl.
Those behind cry: "Forward"!
Those in front cry:
"Back".
Our eyes bear witness
to the grotesque spectacle
called forth from the darkest
corners of Xerxes' Empire.
When muscles failed,
they turned to their magic.
One hundred nations
descend upon us.
The armies of all Asia.
Funneled into this narrow corridor,
their numbers count
for nothing.
They fall by the hundreds.
We send the severed bodies
and the fragile hearts
back to Xerxes' feet.
King Xerxes is displeased
with his generals.
He disciplines them.
Xerxes dispatches his monsters
from half a world away.
They're clumsy beasts.
And the pile of Persian dead
is slippery.
- You still here?
- Someone is got to watch your back.
Well, now, I'm a little busy.
Regroup!
Astinos, my son!
Astinos!
No!
The day wears on.
We lose few...
...but each felled is a friend
or dearest blood.
And upon seeing the headless
body of his own young son,
the captain breaks rank.
He goes wild, blood drunk.
Captain's cries of pain
at the loss of his son
are more frightening to the enemy
than the deepest battle drums.
It takes three men
to restrain him
and bring him back
to our own.
The day is ours.
No songs are sung.
Your gods were cruel
to shape you so, friend Ephialtes.
The Spartans, too,
were cruel to reject you.
But I am kind.
Everything you could
ever desire.
Every happiness you can imagine.
Every pleasure your fellow Greeks
and your false gods have denied you.
I will grant you.
For I am kind.
Embrace me as your king
and as your god.
Yes!
Lead my soldiers
to the hidden path
that empties behind
the cursed Spartans,
and your joys will be endless.
Yes, I want it all.
Wealth, women.
And one more thing.
I want an uniform.
Done.
You will find
that I am kind.
Unlike the cruel Leonidas
that demanded that you stand,
I require only that you kneel.
Beautiful night.
Yes, but I did not ask you here
for small talk, Theron.
I'm assured of that.
You've never spared
words with me.
Can I offer you something?
A drink perhaps?
Is it poison?
Sorry to disappoint you,
it's only water.
I'm told it's been arranged
for you to go before the council.
Yes.
I need your help
in winning votes to send
the army north to our king.
Yes.
I can see the two of us
standing together.
Me, politician, thou, warrior.
Our voices as one.
But why would I want
to do that?
It proves you care
for a king
who, right now, fights
for the very water we drink.
True.
But this is politics,
not war.
- Leonidas is an idealist.
- I know your kind too well.
You send men to slaughter
for your own gain.
Your husband, our king, has taken
300 of our finest to slaughter.
He's broken our laws and left
without the council's consent.
- I'm simply a realist.
- You're an opportunist.
You're as foolish as Leonidas
if you think men
don't have a price in this world.
All men are not created equal.
That's the Spartan code, my little queen.
I admire your passion.
But don't think that you,
a woman, even a queen,
can walk into the council's chamber
and sway the minds of men.
I own that chamber.
As if it were built
with these hands.
I could crush the life
out of you right now.
You will go before the council
but your words will fall in deaf ears.
Leonidas will receive
no reinforcements,
and if he returns, without my help,
he would go to jail or worse.
- Do you love your Sparta?
- Yes.
- And your king?
- I do.
Your husband fights
for his land,
and his love.
What do you have to offer?
In return for my word that
I'll help you send our army north.
What does a realist
want from his queen?
I think you know.
This will not be over quickly.
You will not enjoy this.
I am not your king.
Dilios!
I trust that scracth
hasn't made you useless.
Hardly, my lord.
It's just an eye.
The gods saw fit
to grace me with a spare.
And the captain?
Curses the gods
and mourns alone.
Leonidas!
We are undone.
Undone I tell you.
- Destroyed.
- Daxos, calm yourself!
A hunchback traitor has led
Xerxes' Immortals
to the hidden goat path
behind us.
The Phocians you posted there
were scattered without a fight.
This battle is over, Leonidas!
This battle is over
when I say it is over!
By morning, the Immortals
will surround us.
The Hot Gates will fall.
Spartans!
Prepare for glory!
Glory?
Have you gone mad?
There is no glory to be had now.
Only retreat or surrender
or death.
That is an easy choice for us,
Arcadian.
Spartans never retreat.
Spartans never surrender.
Go. Spread the word.
Let every Greek assembled
know the truth of this.
Let each amongst them
search his own soul.
And while you're at it,
search your own.
My men will leave with me.
Godspeed, Leonidas.
Children! Children!
Gather round.
No retreat.
No surrender.
That is Spartan law.
And by Spartan law,
we will stand and fight.
And die.
A new age has begun.
An age of freedom.
And all will know that
three hundred Spartans
gave their last breath
to defend it!
My friend.
I have lived my entire life
without regret until now.
It's not that my son gave up
his life for his country.
It's just that I never told him
I loved him the most.
That he stood by me
with honor.
That he was all that
was best in me.
My heart is broken
for your loss.
Heart?
I have filled my heart
with hate.
Good.
Dilios!
Let's take a walk.
Yes, my lord.
But, sire, I'm fit.
I'm ready for battle.
That you are
one of the finest.
But you have another talent
unlike any other Spartan.
You will deliver
my final orders to the council
with force and verve.
Tell them my story.
Make every Greek know
what happened here.
You'll have a grand
tale to tell.
A tale of victory.
Victory.
Yes, my lord.
Sire, any message...?
...for the queen?
None that need be spoken.
Hundreds leave.
A handful stay.
Only one looks back.
Spartans!
Ready your breakfast
and eat hearty.
For tonight we dine in Hell!
May I give the floor now to the wife
of Leonidas and queen of Sparta.
Councilmen.
I stand before you
not only as your queen.
I come to you as a mother.
I come to you as a wife.
I come to you
as a Spartan woman.
with great humility.
I am not here to represent
Leonidas.
His actions speak louder
than my words ever could.
I am here for all those voices
which cannot be heard.
Mothers, daughters, fathers, sons.
Three hundred families
that bleed for our rights
and for the very principles
this room is built upon.
We're at war, gentlemen.
We must send the entire spartan
army to aid our king
in the preservation of not just
ourselves but of our children.
Send the army for
the preservation of liberty.
Send it for justice.
Send it for law and order.
Send it for reason.
But, most importantly,
send our army for hope.
Hope that the king and his men have
not been wasted in the pages of history.
That their courage
bonds us together.
That we are made stronger
by their actions.
And that your choices today
reflect their bravery.
Three hundred.
Moving.
Eloquent, passionate.
But it doesn't change the fact
that your husband has brought war upon us.
You are wrong.
Xerxes brought it forth
and before that,
his father, Darius, at Marathon.
The Persians will not stop until
the only shelter we will find
is rubble and chaos.
This chamber needs
no history lesson, my queen.
Then what is the lesson
you would like to leave?
Shall I begin to enumerate
all of them?
Honor, duty, glory.
You speak of honor?
Duty? Glory?
But what of adultery?
- How dare you?
- How dare I?
Watch her, carefully.
She is a trickster
in true form.
Do not play with the members
of this sacred chambers, my queen.
Just hours ago, you offered
yourself to me.
Were I a weaker man,
I'd have her scent on me still.
- This is outrage.
- Ah, the hypocrite speaks.
Did you not receive
a similar payment?
Which you took in exchange for her
having an audience with these noble men.
- That is a lie.
- Is it?
Was he not, by your invitation, asked
to come the king's bedchamber?
The very bed where you attempted
to negotiate with me
so vigorously.
You look shocked.
A bribe of the flesh,
gentlemen,
whilst her husband
promotes anarchy and war.
Words escape even
the most cunning tongues.
My little whore queen.
What queen-like behaviour!
Remove her from this chamber
before she infects us further
with her inglorious
and filthy self.
This will not be over quickly.
You will not enjoy this.
I am not your queen.
Traitor.
Traitor, traitor, traitor.
Leonidas.
My compliments.
And congratulations.
You surely have turned calamity
to victory.
Despite your insufferable
arrogance,
the God King has come to admire
Spartan valor
and fighting skills.
You will make a mighty ally.
Yield, Leonidas.
Use your reason.
Think of your men.
I beg you.
Listen to your fellow Greek.
He can attest to the divine
one's generosity.
Despite your several insults,
despite your horrid
blasphemies,
the lord of hosts is prepared
to forgive all.
And more: to reward
your service.
You fight for your lands.
Keep them.
You fight for Sparta.
She will be wealthier and more
powerful than ever before.
You fight for your kingship.
You will be proclaimed warlord
of all Greece.
Answerable only to the one
true master of the world.
Leonidas. Your victory
will be complete.
If you but lay down your arms
and kneel to holy Xerxes.
It's been more than 30 years
since the wind and the winter cold.
And now, as then, it's not
fear that grips him.
Only restlesness.
A heightened sense of things.
The seaborne breeze cooly kissing
the sweat on his chest and neck.
Gulls cawing,
complaining even as they feast
on thousands of floating dead.
The steady breathing
of the 300 at his back.
Ready to die for him,
without a moment's pause.
Every one of them
ready to die.
His helmet is stifling.
His shield is heavy.
Your spear.
You there.
Ephialtes.
May you live forever.
Leonidas, your spear.
Stelios!
Slaughter them!
His helmet was stifling.
It narrowed his vision.
And he must see far.
His shield was heavy.
It threw him off balance.
And his target is far away.
The old ones say we Spartans
have descended from Hercules himself.
Bold Leonidas gives testament
to our bloodline.
His roar is long and loud.
My king.
It's an honor to die at your side.
It's an honor to have lived
at yours.
My queen.
My wife.
My love.
Remember us.
As simple an order
as a king can give.
Remember why we died.
For he did not wish tribute
or song.
No monuments, no poems
of war and valor.
His wish was simple.
Remember us.
He said to me.
That was his hope.
Should any free soul
come across that place
in all the countless
centuries yet to be,
may all our voices whisper to you
from the ageless stones.
Go tell the Spartans,
passerby,
that here, by Spartan law,
we lie.
So my king died...
And my brothers died.
Barely a year ago.
Long I pondered my king's
cryptic talk of victory
and the time has proven
him wise.
For from Greek to free Greek
the word was spread that bold
Leonidas and his 300,
so far from home,
laid down their lives,
not just for Sparta,
but for all Greece and the promise
this country holds.
And now, here on this ragged
patch of earth called Platea,
Xerxes' hordes face obliteration.
Just there, the barbarians huddle.
Sheer terror gripping tight
their hearts with icy fingers.
knowing full well what merciless
horrors they suffered
at the swords and spears
of three hundred.
Yet they stare now,
across the plain,
at 10.000 Spartans,
commanding 30.000 free Greeks.
The enemy outnumbers us
a paltry three to one.
Good odds for any Greek.
This day we rescue a world
from mysticism and tyranny
and usher in a future brighter
that anything we can imagine.
Give thanks, men...
to Leonidas and the
brave three hundred.
To victory!